<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="filter.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <title>Container Provided Filters</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Table of Contents">
<toc/>
</section>

<section name="Introduction">

  <p>Tomcat provides a number of <strong>Filters</strong> which may be
  configured for use with all web applications using
  <code>$CATALINA_BASE/conf/web.xml</code> or may be configured for individual
  web applications by configuring them in the application's
  <code>WEB-INF/web.xml</code>. Each filter is described below.</p>

    <blockquote><em>
    <p>This description uses the variable name $CATALINA_BASE to refer the
    base directory against which most relative paths are resolved. If you have
    not configured Tomcat for multiple instances by setting a CATALINA_BASE
    directory, then $CATALINA_BASE will be set to the value of $CATALINA_HOME,
    the directory into which you have installed Tomcat.</p>
    </em></blockquote>

</section>


<section name="CSRF Prevention Filter">

  <subsection name="Introduction">

    <p>This filter provides basic CSRF protection for a web application. The
    filter assumes that it is mapped to <code>/*</code> and that all URLs
    returned to the client are encoded via a call to
    <code>HttpServletResponse#encodeRedirectURL(String)</code> or
    <code>HttpServletResponse#encodeURL(String)</code>.</p>
    
    <p>This filter prevents CSRF by generating a nonce and storing it in the
    session. URLs are also encoded with the same nonce. When the next request is
    received the nonce in the request is compared to the nonce in the session
    and only if they are the same is the request allowed to continue.</p>
    
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Filter Class Name">

    <p>The filter class name for the CSRF Prevention Filter is
    <strong><code>org.apache.catalina.filters.CsrfPreventionFilter</code>
    </strong>.</p>

  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Initialisation parameters">

    <p>The CSRF Prevention Filter supports the following initialisation
    parameters:</p>

    <attributes>

      <attribute name="entryPoints" required="false">
        <p>A comma separated list of URLs that will not be tested for the
        presence of a valid nonce. They are used to provide a way to navigate
        back to a protected application after having navigated away from it.
        Entry points will be limited to HTTP GET requests and should not trigger
        any security sensitive actions.</p>
      </attribute>
      
      <attribute name="nonceCacheSize" required="false">
        <p>The number of previously issued nonces that will be cached on a LRU
        basis to support parallel requests, limited use of the refresh and back
        in the browser and similar behaviors that may result in the submission
        of a previous nonce rather than the current one. If not set, the default
        value of 5 will be used.</p>
      </attribute>
      
      <attribute name="randomClass" required="false">
        <p>The name of the class to use to generate nonces. The class must be an
        instance of <code>java.util.Random</code>. If not set, the default value
        of <code>java.security.SecureRandom</code> will be used.</p>
      </attribute>
      
    </attributes>
    
  </subsection>

</section>


<section name="Failed Request Filter">

  <subsection name="Introduction">

    <p>This filter triggers parameters parsing in a request and rejects the
    request if some parameters were skipped during parameter parsing because
    of parsing errors or request size limitations (such as
    <code>maxParameterCount</code> attribute in a
    <a href="http.html">Connector</a>).
    This filter can be used to ensure that none parameter values submitted by
    client are lost.</p>

    <p>Note that parameter parsing may consume the body of an HTTP request, so
    caution is needed if the servlet protected by this filter uses
    <code>request.getInputStream()</code> or <code>request.getReader()</code>
    calls. In general the risk of breaking a web application by adding this
    filter is not so high, because parameter parsing does check content type
    of the request before consuming the request body.</p>

    <p>The request is rejected with HTTP status code 400 (Bad Request).</p>

  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Filter Class Name">

    <p>The filter class name for the Failed Request Filter is
    <strong><code>org.apache.catalina.filters.FailedRequestFilter</code>
    </strong>.</p>

  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Initialisation parameters">

    <p>The Failed Request Filter does not support any initialization parameters.</p>

  </subsection>

</section>


</body>


</document>
